CHAPTER 7

Dutch Slave Trade from
Nagapattinam to Colombo, Banten,
Jakarta, Melaka, Cape Town and the
Social Realities of the Enslaved,
1655-1791

Portuguese private traders in Nagapattinam developed slave trade with Melaka and Manila towards the end of the sixteenth century and it continued till 1658 when the Dutch captured and occupied the Portuguese settlement.1 The individuals made profit from their personal small scale slave trade, particularly because they had access to the same transportation network in which they could sell their slaves at sites where they could obtain higher prices. The Dutch Company’s slave trade was different from private Portuguese slave trade. The Dutch Company had legalized slave trade at Nagapattinam which developed between the nodes of Jakarta which functioned as the Capital of the Dutch East India Company and with Colombo and Galle in Sri Lanka that had emerged as part of a larger grid of migration of the Dutch maritime empire. The Dutch developed a new type of slaves, called company slaves which differed from existing modes of bondage in the coastal Tamil area in which private slaves were owned by individuals. The Dutch East India Company used mobility and coercion which were the key elements in mobilizing labour and maintaining an order.

THE EARLY SLAVE TRADE BY THE DUTCH IN
NAGAPATTINAM AREA, 1655-1656

The Dutch explored the possibilities to purchase slaves in Nagapattinam area and they could manage to transport slaves on a large scale in 1655 to Colombo in Sri Lanka.2

TABLE 7.1: PURCHASE AND EXPORT OF SLAVES
IN DUTCH SHIPS FROM NAGAPATTINAM
TO COLOMBO, 1655-1656

Year | Month | Slaves (men, women)
1655 | January | 3,695
1656 | January | 500
TOTAL | | 4,195

Source: See Note.3

These slaves were employed in the fortification works at Colombo in the Dutch factory. Thus the Dutch purchased and exported 4,195 slaves from Nagapattinam area between 1655 and 1656.

TRANSPORTING WAR PRISONERS DECLARED
AS SLAVES FROM NAGAPATTINAM
TO JAKARTA, 1658

The Dutch were very much desirous to attack and occupy the Portuguese settlement of Nagapattinam. On 20 July 1658 they made attempts and after three days Nagapattinam fell into the hands of Major Van der Laan. Many Portuguese residents fled from the place. After two days (25 July 1658), the Dutch ship Leeuwin sailed away, 50 people mostly married, including women and children from Nagapattinam to Jakarta were captured as war prisoners and declared as slaves.4 On 2 September 1658 war prisoners were again transported from Nagapattinam to Bengal in Avondster the ship for onward transmission to Jakarta but the actual number of persons had not been mentioned.5 After two days (4 September 1658), the sloop Narasapur sailed away from Nagapattinam carrying 100 worthless people and again another sailing vessel called Piply took 70 worthless persons to Jakarta.6

On 9 September 1658 it is mentioned that 210 people from Nagapattinam who were mostly women and children, including taupases and slaves were taken to Jakarta.7 On 27 October 1658 a sailing vessel called Piply took 73 persons and Avondster, another ship carried 200 Portuguese prisoners of war and slaves from Nagapattinam to Jakarta.8 One has no idea as to the fate of all these war prisoners and slaves, whether they were further transported elsewhere to Dutch trading settlements in South East Asia or employed in Jakarta itself.

THE GROWTH OF SLAVE TRADE AT
NAGAPATTINAM UNDER THE
DUTCH, 1658-1661

The Dutch were permitted by the nayak of Thanjavur to reside and trade in Nagapattinam for three years only. The contract was renewed on 5 January 1662 and the company was permitted to pay half per cent toll on all goods imported and exported.9 The officials of the Dutch East India Company in Jakarta instructed the Dutch in Nagapattinam to buy and transport slaves since there was demand for labour in Amboina in 1659-60. The company officials in Amboina reported that the small pox epidemic that had broken out in 1660, had caused deaths and so there was a shortage of labour to look after the new plants of cloves. Further it has also been stated that the rebels had destroyed the plants and there was need to plant new trees because the existing plants had become 5 to 30 years old.10

The invasion of Bijapur army on the kingdom of Thanjavur made it impossible for the purchase of slaves during that period. The Dutch factor of Nagapattinam was instructed to supply slaves to Sri Lanka in 1659 and he arranged with the help of local agents and traders. The purchase price of a slave in Nagapattinam then was stated to be one real. As the price was very cheap, 5,000 slaves were purchased and transported on 11 September 1659 from Nagapattinam to Colombo in Sri Lanka.11 It was at this time that the VOC had also issued an order on 27 June 1659 prohibiting the transport of slaves by the Tamil merchants in their ships from Nagapattinam to Sri Lanka.12 Following the ban, slave trade by private merchants came into operation in a clandestine fashion. However, the Dutch made all attempts to curb the private trade in slaves. The company made attempts to purchase and it transported slaves on 14 August 1660. Most of the slaves were peasants from the region of Thanjavur.13

It is reported that out of the 5,000 slaves transported, 3,000 persons were considered absolutely worthless in Sri Lanka by November 1660.14 As a result 425 workers hailing from Thanjavur were sent back in ships to Nagapattinam and the costs of the return transport had to be borne by the agents.15

There were plenty of slaves owned by Europeans in Colombo and these slaves were employed in private houses. Dutch burghers sailed to Nagapattinam and they purchased slaves. Prospective native traders also carried many slaves to Colombo in ships which is reported on 2 April 1660.16 Slaves transported were branded with a small company mark (VOC) on the right thigh or arm. This was done so that company slaves could not be sold several times. It was also used as a means to differentiate between private slaves and the free labourers who were also transported from Nagapattinam to Colombo.

Those slaves and free labourers who arrived were not familiar with the building construction works in Colombo because they were farmers, weavers and artisans. Some died in a year. Many slaves hailing from Thanjavur area were released and they were allotted land for cultivation. It is reported that more than 900 slaves were employed in cultivating the lands around Colombo by 1662.17

In a record of 26 January 1661 one finds mention of 400 slaves waiting for the transport in the ships of the Dutch Company from Nagapattinam.18 War and famine had brought misery to people in the region of Nagapattinam. Many came forward to sell themselves as slaves and this facilitated the slave trade. The Dutch exported 6,793 slaves from Nagapattinam to Colombo between 1659 and 1661. These ships sailed carrying slaves in the period between January and April during the north-east monsoon.

TABLE 7.2: PURCHASE AND EXPORT OF SLAVES
IN DUTCH SHIPS FROM NAGAPATTINAM TO
COLOMBO, 1659-1661

Year | Month Date | Slaves (men, women)
1659 | | 5,000
1660 | 1-14 January | 1,393 (500 men, 860 women, 33 children)
1661 | July | 400
TOTAL | | 6,793

Source: See Note.19

The Dutch purchased a total of 1,461 slaves at Nagapattinam in 1660 they exported to the ports of Banten, Melaka and Jakarta and the details are given as follows.

TABLE 7.3: PURCHASE AND EXPORT OF SLAVES IN
DUTCH SHIPS FROM NAGAPATTINAM TO
BANTEN, 1660

Year | Month Date | Name of the Ship | Slaves (men, women)
1660 | May | Kabelijau | 46

Source: See Note.20

TABLE 7.4: PURCHASE AND EXPORT OF SLAVES
IN DUTCH SHIPS FROM NAGAPATTINAM
TO JAKARTA, 1660

Year | Month Date | Name of the Ship | Slaves (men, women)
1660 | March | Nieuwpoort | 54
1660 | 30 March-9 August | Many ships | 700
1660 | May | Kabelijau | 77
1660 | July | Hercules | 220
1660 | July | Leeuwin | 151
TOTAL | | | 1,202

Source: See Note.21

TABLE 7.5: PURCHASE AND EXPORT OF SLAVES
IN DUTCH SHIPS FROM NAGAPATTINAM
TO MELAKA, 1660

Year | Month Date | Name of the Ship | Slaves (men, women)
1660 | July | Hercules | 54
1660 | July | Leeuwin | 99
1660 | November | Rode Leeuw | 60
TOTAL | | | 213

Source: See Note.22

An eyewitness account of Nagapattinam in 1661 vividly portrayed the situation. It was depicted that the famine had worsened to such an extent that entire villages, hamlets and settlements had been depopulated, leaving hardly anyone. Dead bodies were lying scattered in dry tanks, along common roads, indeed, even on the streets of the city of Nagapattinam. Those who had survived, resembled lifeless corpses more than living people. They cried along the fields and roads for a single meal to fill their empty stomachs before dying. In short, the account ended saying that the miseries and sufferings were such, that no pen could describe the extremity of the situation.23

At that time the Dutch Company officials began to portray their participation in the slave trade and traffic as a work of Protestant Christian charity. Laurens Pit the Dutch Governor of the Coromandel Coast (1652-63) informed the Directors of the Company in August 1660 that it was indisputable that the purchase of these poor people was a work of compassion since they would perish otherwise, as happened to those who were turned away.24 Elaborating on Pit’s Christian humanitarian theme, Johan Maetsuycker (1653-78) the Dutch Governor-General and his Council mentioned in Jakarta in November 1660 that their intention was that the purchase of slaves of both the elderly and the young would continue indiscriminately, especially when they were members of a single family as was often the case. If the Dutch Company accepted only the young and turned down the old, the latter would perish, which had already occurred quite often. This would not conform to the Christian compassion because to accept the children and leaving the parents to die in their presence, or to accept the men and turn down the women, would be harsh. He finally ended saying that it would be also unacceptable to the Lord God.25

The Portuguese missionaries being Catholics, noted the Dutch slave trading methods and activities and so criticized them. Antão Proença (1625-66) the Portuguese Jesuit reported and condemned the Dutch for buying slaves in exchange for rice at Nagapattinam in 1662. He wrote that it was shameful and eternal shame to the Dutch, who had the cruelty to speculate on the misery of the Tamils. The Dutch attracted the natives to the port of Nagapattinam on the coast by using abundant nourishment as bait. When the slave numbers were considerable in the godowns, they transported slaves silently in Dutch ships to various places.26 Antão Proença also referred to the widespread famine in the region, which he attributed to the vagaries of war and the failure of the monsoon. He stated that the mortality was so great that corpses were heaped up in great piles.27 The Dutch also explored the purchase of slaves at Sadurangapattinam and the slaves bought in 1663 were sent to Nagapattinam for export to Melaka.

TABLE 7.6: PURCHASE AND EXPORT OF SLAVES IN
DUTCH SHIPS FROM SADURANGAPATTINAM
TO MELAKA, 1663

Year | Month Date | Name of the Ship | Slaves (men, women)
1663 | June | Cabelijauw | 5

Source: See Note.28

A Dutch record of 21 September 1668 states that customs duty on slaves was exempted at Melaka for Dutch ships. The non-Dutch ships had to pay 20 per cent customs duty. Slaves were made duty free to provide the much-needed labour in Melaka.29 In 1687, it was reported that 100 slaves had been transported from Nagapattinam on the Coromandel Coast to Melaka, because the scarce coolies were too expensive, costing 8 stuivers per day.30

REDISTRIBUTION OF NAGAPATTINAM SLAVES
BY THE DUTCH COMPANY FROM COLOMBO
IN SRI LANKA IN SHIPS TO JAKARTA
IN INDONESIA, 1678-1683

Dutch records often mention that the slaves of Nagapattinam transported to Sri Lanka had been re-transported to South East Asia. In 1679 slaves from Nagapattinam who reached Sri Lanka numbering 100, were sent to Melaka costing 3,153 florins. It is reported that 11 slaves died during the voyage.31 In the same year (1679) it is mentioned that 900 slaves of Nagapattinam were transferred from Sri Lanka to Jakarta.32 The Dutch East India Company in Jakarta found it difficult to procure slaves from Timor and so these slaves numbering 1,000 hailing from Nagapattinam were sent to Jakarta. As these slaves were mainly women and children, they were not suitable for work in the mines.33 The next year (1678) 360 slaves of Nagapattinam were sent from Colombo to Jakarta and 900 slaves were shipped again in 1679 from Colombo to Jakarta.34 It was reported in March 1683 that in Colombo in Sri Lanka there were no longer any surplus Company slaves for re-transportation to Jakarta in Indonesia. There were 1,160 male and female slaves that could still work, while 307 slaves were unable to work due to old age and infirmities, 209 slaves were practically worn out, 15 slaves had absconded and 99 slave children attended schools besides 123 infant slaves.35

Rijkloff van Goens the Dutch Governor of Sri Lanka (1662-3, 1665-75) reported in his various letters of 1661-2 to the Governor-General in Jakarta and also to the Directors of the Dutch East India Company in Amsterdam in 1675, 1676, 1677 and 1680 that divine providence had made the slaves come to Sri Lanka in order to repopulate the lands there and to support the Dutch Company’s designs.36 Dutch export of slaves continued from Nagapattinam and one finds weavers and artisans who had been exported to Jaffna on 29 March 1667.

Besides slaves one finds many free labourers who were also purchased and sent to Colombo due to labour shortage there. It is mentioned in Dutch sources that the Sinhalese were too lazy and not greatly disposed to take up fortification work and also to dig the earth and do other related irrigation works.37 In 1674 the Dutch Company in Colombo abolished the use of hired labour in Colombo. Hence a number of hired workers had not been transported from Nagapattinam and their number dwindled.38 Dutch records mention that the practice of coolies and hired workers who were brought to Colombo to work at the fortifications had been stopped and discontinued since 1674.39

When Ekoji I (1674-84) became the ruler of Thanjavur in 1675 the Dutch were allowed to continue their trade at Nagapattinam. They continued to buy slaves and exported them. The Dutch Company planned to utilize those textile worker slaves who had been skilled exported from Nagapattinam to Colombo. They were asked to weave cloth, also engaged in textile dyeing and helped in the organization and production of cloth in Sri Lanka.40

The Dutch private traders were prohibited to trade in slaves in 1685. The reason was that the Dutch Company itself was the main slave trader.41 Incoming coolie workers and slaves reached illegally in ships from Nagapattinam through private traders to Colombo where they were detected in 1692. They were confiscated and put to work at fortifications in Colombo.42 During 1690-91 slave purchase at Nagapattinam also came to a halt because the famine situation had improved.

THE SLAVE PURCHASES AND TRADE AT
NAGAPATTINAM UNDER THE
DUTCH, 1694-1704

The Dutch purchased 5,000 slaves in 1694 when slaves were available for sale at the rate of one real per head at Nagapattinam. In 1695 one finds 3,500 slaves were imported to Jaffna and the traders paid the import duties. Hendrick Zwaardecroon the commander of Jaffnapatnam noted that import of more people meant more mouths to be fed, while rice was more dear than labour at the time. He stated explicitly that he would have preferred if traders had brought in rice rather than humans.43 Again 3,859 slaves were purchased by the Dutch in Nagapattinam and exported by 30 November 1696. Thus the relationship between rice and slave market is also an interesting line of enquiry. The Dutch continued to purchase and transported 1,741 slaves from Nagapattinam to Colombo in 1697.44 Thus the Dutch had exported 14,100 slaves in total from Nagapattinam between 1694 and 1697.

The Dutch continued to purchase and transport slaves whenever available and possible from Nagapattinam to Colombo. It had transported 1,582 slaves in 1704 when crops failed in the region.45 Thus famines, warfare and crop failure had largely helped to the export of slaves to Sri Lanka.

The Dutch East India Company shifted its trading headquarters on the Coromandel Coast from Pulicat to Nagapattinam in 1690. The Dutch continued to purchase slaves in Nagapattinam whenever possible. The poverty of people and famines in the region facilitated. The Dutch Company built slave lodges in the trading settlements on the Coromandel Coast to facilitate export. The plan of the Dutch fort of Nagapattinam in 1700 by Issack de Graff the map-maker shows the slave rooms, halls and also secret chambers where slaves were lodged and fed before transportation in ships.46 The plan and drawing of the Dutch factory of Sadurangapattinam in the seventeenth century by Issack de Graff also mentions the slave cottages where slaves stayed before export.47 The plan of the Dutch factory at Porto Novo in 1700 drawn by Issack de Graff refers to slave cottages built where the purchased slaves were lodged.48 The plan of the Dutch fort of Geldria at Pulicat in 1708 prepared by Jan Christianensz Toorzee refers to the chambers of the slaves kept for export.49 Thus one finds extensive arrangements were made at Dutch settlements for the stay of the slaves before shipping overseas.

SLAVE EXPORTS FROM NAGAPATTINAM
TO AFRICA, 1705-1739

The Dutch Company exported slaves to Cape Town and used slave labour widely. It ordered that slaves who were found on the ships returning to the Netherlands were not to become free, but were sentenced to remain as slave for the rest of their lives in the possession of the company.50 Such measures were meant chiefly to target the slave owners who brought the slaves illegally on board the homeward bound ships. Hence slaves were compelled to be sold before sailing to the Netherlands from Cape Town.

The Dutch Company also brought convict labour in large numbers as slaves to be employed in Cape Town. It included company servants, exiled criminals and political prisoners. They were used to labour on the public works. Some slaves kept by the Company were distributed to burghers on credit, and were privately owned. There were around 300 privately owned slaves in Cape Town in 1690s.51

A 10 years old boy named Chinnan was sold by his mother in Nagapattinam because of her utter poverty and lack of means for livelihood to an employee of the Dutch Company. Slave supplies from Nagapattinam were plentiful during the period of economic crisis. In 1705 Chinnan the slave and his sister had reached Cape Town as exported. One finds that Chinnan was owned by a farmer in the Stellenbosch district. He ran away to the place of his sister in Cape Town when he could no longer endure ill-treatment.52

The directors of the Dutch East India Company asked the opinion of M.P. de Chavonnes in their letter dated 24 June 1716, regarding the governor of Cape and his Council on a range of issues relating to coal, agricultural production, trade and labour. In terms of labour, the directors wanted to know whether the immigration of free European labour would be preferable to the then current reliance on slaves. The Governor believed that free European farm labour would be more expensive and troublesome than slaves. He reported that wages would have to be covered for all work done not only in the fields but also for the daily work done by slaves. He said that doing manual work could not be demanded from the Europeans in this weather. He added that the Dutch Company would find it more useful and cheaper to keep slaves than European farm labour. Further, as wine and other strong drinks were fairly cheap, all workmen and the lower classes were addicted to drink, it would be extremely difficult to restrain them and keep them confined to their duties. He said that the Dutch Company had already been provided amply with drunkards in the Cape and their hands had been not free.53

C. van Beaumont and J. Cruse the Dutch officials opined on 10 February 1717 that Europeans would not be found nearly as much of use as slaves, particularly in the case of daily menial tasks. They said that it had been more fitting for the slaves rather than Europeans who could be used.54

Slaves exported from Nagapattinam and the miserable life of the young Tamil slaves exported to Cape Town had been revealing. Suppudu (Cupido) was a slave in Cape Town and he was brought to trial in 1739. According to records he could no longer bear the loneliness of being the only slave employed in the household. He struggled very much to adapt himself to the new cultural context.55 He told his mistress that he was not used to wearing the clothes that she gave. He complained that he had worked alone for two years. While attempting to stab his mistress he declared that ‘it would be better if I murder you, your husband and your child, and that I flay you open like flecked fish, and then do me as well’.56 Suppudu had felt alienation and loneliness strongly.

PURCHASE AND SALE OF SLAVES BY THE NAVAL
OFFICERS OF THE DUTCH COMPANY ON
THE COROMANDEL COAST, 1737-1743

Some slaves from Coromandel Coast had been found sold to the middle level officers of the ships and also to high ranking officials of the Dutch Company during 1737 and 1743. Januarij a male slave of the Coromandel Coast was sold in 1737 by an unknown person (name not recorded) to Constantia Amalia Falk at 50 rix dollars. Joseph, another male slave of Coromandel Coast was sold in 1740 by Jan Jacobsz Gouda, a nurse of a returning ship to Adam Amie, another nurse on a ship at 60 rix dollars. Sisnander a male slave of Coromandel Coast was sold in 1741 by joint owners (a surgeon at the company’s hospital and an assistant) to the captain of a ship for 150 Arcot rupees. October, a male slave in 1743 was sold by a junior merchant to another junior merchant of the Dutch Company at 250 Arcot rupees.57

SLAVES EXPORTED FROM NAGAPATTINAM
TO CAPE TOWN, 1763-1775

It is found that old names of the slaves were changed and new names like Januarij and October had been given when sale was made from one person to another. This suggests creating a new identity in the minds of the slave owners. Chinna Thaai the female slave hailing from Nagapattinam was sold thrice and she finally reached Cape Town. She ended up with the Christian name called ‘Rosa’. In Cape Town she was employed in 1763 at Groot Constantia’s wine estate located outside the suburbs of the town.58 Again one notices that Seena a young girl was sold into slavery in Nagapattinam in 1768 and she was exported to Cape Town. She was also called by the name Rosa in 1775 at Cape Town.59

SLAVES EXPORTED TO
SRI LANKA, 1720-1791

Slaves continued to be exported from Nagapattinam and Tuticorin to Sri Lanka. A deed mentions that Louis de Saram Maha Mudaliyar purchased a boy called Maden, renamed Lourens, on 30 December 1728, from a seller called Joan chetti for the price of 12 rix dollars in Tuticorin.60 Unruly slaves in Sri Lanka were exposed to public abuse. The slave offenders were formerly locked by the neck and wrists into wooden framework. Many slaves standing in the pillory died in 1723. The Tamil slave list includes Maalathi, Ayyapan, Chinna Pillai, Latchumi, Muthu, Namasivaayam, Savarimuthu, Chinnakutti, Muthusamy, Karuppan and Kittu.61

The Dutch in Nagapattinam exported slaves to Sri Lanka particularly to Colombo and Galle. A deed signed at Nagapattinam in 1766 had mentioned Spadille, one of the 16 slaves. She was emancipated by Anna Maria Giethoorn and the certificate was signed in 1769.62 A certificate had been signed in Nagapattinam where a slave called Lakshmi (Lechumee in record) belonging to a dealer named Kadhiravan (Cadieraavan). She was freed finally in Sri Lanka in 1787. Thus the legal status and fate of some of the slaves who gained freedom had come to light.63

The prices of slaves purchased by the Dutch on the Coromandel Coast had been mentioned in records. The Tamil male cook Cupido was sold for 70 rix dollars.64 The slave woman called Aurora in 1751 had been referred to as old maid, and so she was sold at a low price of 30 rix dollars.65 Thus the individual variations in salve prices are important to be taken into account.

SOCIAL LIFE OF THE TAMIL SLAVES
IN CAPE TOWN

Slave trade was nominally a Danish company monopoly after 1732, but this was also an illegal trade. Slaves were evidently sent to the Cape for official sale for some years after 1737, but these transactions were on a limited scale. This was a period of labour shortage in the Dutch colony for the heavy work involved on company projects. Slaves brought from Pazhaverkadu, Pondicherry, Tranquebar, Nagapattinam, and Manapaadu to Cape Town got married to slaves who had come from Jaffna in Sri Lanka and from Makassar, Timor and Amboina in South East Asia. These slaves gave birth to slave children. Johanna of Madras was born at Cape in 1709. Johannes de Jong was the daughter of Moses of Pazhaverkadu and she was born in 1752 at Cape Town.

TABLE 7.7: MARRIAGES OF TAMIL SLAVES IN
CAPE TOWN, 1702-1788

Year | Male | Female
1702 | Arend of Coromandel | Helena from Makassar
1702 | Arend of Coromandel | Maria of Nagapattinam
1709 | Classen of Coromandel | Catharina of Nagapattinam
1721 | Antony of Pazhaverkadu | Esperanca of Nagapattinam
1721 | Claas of Coromandel | Helena of Timor
1725 | Classen of Coromandel | Johanna de Ryk of Bengal
1732 | Moses of Pulicat | Cecilia of Jaffna
1746 | Francis of Coromandel | Agatha of Java
1746 | Francois Pondicherry | Rosalie from Pondicherry
1774 | Frederick of Coromandel | Johanna of Tranquebar
1787 | Nicholaas Christophe | Magdalena of Nagapattinam
1788 | Adam of Manapaadu | Catharina Maria of Amboina

Source: Hans F. Heese, Cape Melting Pot: The Role and Status of the Mixed Population at the Cape, 1652-1795, trs. Delia Robertson, Cape, 2015, pp. 27-8, 96, 101-2, 219-21, 224-5, 230.

The Dutch continued to obtain and export slaves as late as 1791-2. The letter of Sir Charles Oakley, the English Governor at Madras in 1792 pointed out that the traffic in slaves for export had received great encouragement by the permission granted by the Dutch Company to the contractors. As a result, numerous intermediaries had been found active and doing the purchase and transported slaves under the Dutch banner.66

To conclude, it may be said that the Dutch records allow one to have glimpses of slaves as human beings with their own emotions and personalities. One finds how slaves have fallen prey to enslavement including slavery prevalent including prisoners of war. The slave labour differed substantially from period to period, as a result of changes that occurred in the system in tune with the global regime of slavery. Slaves and slavery had great shifts in response to the socio-economic order.

The Dutch Company increasingly used slavery, the main form of coerced labour, as an effective mode of production and also more as part of labour-intensive routes to economic development. Slavery had been an integral and dynamic part of a permanently developing Dutch empire in Asia, globally connected and increasingly capitalist economic system. This study points out that slavery as a modern, dynamic economic system of production and the coercion was not the only key element crucial to the systems of labour, especially for slave labour, it was increasingly accepted that transportation and mobility was one of the crucial elements underpinning the systems. Within the Dutch shipping network, the port of Colombo was second in importance only to Jakarta. Famines and warfare supplied slaves from Nagapattinam for transport to Colombo. The slave traffic between the Coromandel Coast and Colombo was particularly significant. The Dutch Company in Nagapattinam had purchased and exported 28,136 slaves in total to Sri Lanka between 1655 and 1704. They re-exported 2,160 slaves of Nagapattinam in ships from Colombo to Jakarta in 1679. There were 1,913 slaves hailing from Nagapattinam who were employed at a Colombo factory in 1683. The slaves of Nagapattinam who were brought to Colombo were sent to Galle, Jaffna, Trincomalee and Negombo to meet the labour needs of the Dutch Company. Such minute details could not be traced from records. These Dutch Company slaves of Nagapattinam had also worked on fortifications and in the agriculture sector there.

What one finds here on the history of labour relations is important. One finds subdivisions into reciprocal, tributary, independent, slave and wage-labour relations. Wage labour has been especially associated with free wage labour, in the form of casual wage labour as neatly recorded in Dutch records. The form of contract labour (indentured) has been absent in Dutch Company records of Nagapattinam. Free persons have been referred to in Dutch records and they performed casual wage labour side by side with slaves. According to Dutch records the term coolie pointed out to wages and associated with the person employed. It is not associated with unskilled and menial labour. The term is of Tamil origin in etymology and confronted the creation of social underclass, neither slaves nor clients of patrons in the seventeenth century. The meaning of the term coolie changed later and it became a synonym for contract labour both the formally and informally bonded.

Slaves in Tamil society were integrated to the household and there was a move from household slaves to workers to be employed in the Dutch factories overseas. Debt slavery developed in times of catastrophes like famines and there was no link or association of slavery with race in Tamil country. Thus the study has emphasized the historical role of other labour relations beyond the European binary of slavery and free wage labour. Bringing together all forms of bondage and coercion (slavery, debt bondage, etc.) in European and colonial contexts, indicate the commonalities between these different groups of workers while not preventing a detailed analysis of their particularities, and making it possible to acknowledge the combined role of multiple coercive labour relations in shaping the modern world. There was definitely an absence of freedom and equality and it would be interesting to know how the idea of heaven had been constructed and shaped in the Hindu religion and Tamil society. Ignoring the moral implications of the slave trade by the Dutch, it is concluded it was a trade, as compared with other trades. The slave traffic and trade from the Tamil Coast played a strategic role in the Asian commercial system. The Dutch procured the necessary labour, in the form of coerced human strength, for the production in Indonesia and Sri Lanka. This means that an approach based on a calculation of the ‘alternatives’ or the ‘opportunity costs’ cannot be applied. This approach is grounded in the idea that the production factors that were put into the slave trade would also have contributed to the economy of the Netherlands, had they been invested in other sectors.

NOTES

1. S. Jeyaseela Stephen, Subaltern Lives: Tamil History and Society from Medieval to Early Modern Age, Kalpaz, New Delhi, 2019, pp. 144-7.

2. Tapan Raychaudhri, Jan Company in Coromandel, 1605-1690: A Study in the Interrelations of European Commerce and Traditional Economies, The Hague, 1962, p. 166.

3. Nationaal Archief (hereafter NA), Den Haag, Mss VOC 1232, fl. 382; VOC, 1231, fl. 795.

4. NA, VOC 1227, fl. 289v, Letter of Van Goens from Jaffna to Jakarta.

5. NA, VOC 1231 fl. 155.

6. NA, VOC 1231, fl. 174, Letter of Laurens Pit from Pulicat dated 4 September 1658.

7. NA, VOC 1227 fl. 94, Letter of Van Goens to Laurens Pit from Pulicat dated 9 September 1658.

8. NA, VOC 1227, fl. 194, Letter of Ougly dated 27 October 1658.

9. S. Jeyaseela Stephen, From European Dwelling Settlements to Global Cities: Ports of the Tamil Coast and the Colonial Modernity, Primus, Delhi, 2021, p. 117.

10. W. Ph. Coolhas, ed., Generale Missiven van de Gouverneurs-Generaal en Raden Aan Heren XVII der Verenigde Oostindische Compagnie, 9 vols., ’S Gravenhage, 1960-84 (hereafter GM), vol. III (1655-74), p. 315 (16 December 1660).

11. NA, VOC 1231, fl. 795.

12. L. Hovy, Ceylonees Plakkaatboek: Plakkaten en Andere Wetten Uitgevaardigd door het Nederlandse Bestuur op Ceylon, 1638-1796, 2 vols., Hilversum, Verloren, 1991, vol. I, pp. 46-8.

13. GM, vol. III, p. 175, pp. 335-66 (24 October 1655-6); NA, VOC 1232, fl. 382.

14. NA, VOC 1233, fls. 171-8, fls. 174-5 (22 November 1660).

15. Sri Lanka National Archives (hereafter SLNA), VOC Archives, Record group 1, Inventory number 9, fls. 238v-239, Minutes of the Governor and Council in Colombo dated 16 November 1660.

16. NA, VOC 1233, fls. 157-8.

17. NA, VOC 1234, fls. 25r-v; SLNA, 2712, Colombo Diary, fl. 57.

18. GM, vol. III, p. 335 (26 January 1661).

19. NA, VOC 1232, fl. 382; VOC 1233, fls. 25v-26, Laurnes Pit in Pulicat to Batavia, 24 March 1660; VOC 1232, fls. 382-3, Laurnes Pit in Pulicat to Heeren XVII, 9 August 1660; NA, VOC 1236, fls. 576, 600.

20. NA, VOC 1233, fls. 41v-42.

21. NA, VOC 1233, fls. 23-4; VOC, 1232, fls. 382-3, Laurnes Pit in Pulicat to Heeren XVII, 9 August 1660; VOC 1233, fls. 41v-42; VOC 1233, fls. 45, 46, 46v; VOC 1233, fls. 50v, 53.

22. NA, VOC 1233, fls. 45, 46, 46v; VOC 1233, fls. 50v, 53; VOC 1232, fl. 82; GM, 16 December 1660.

23. GM, vol. III, pp. 355-6, see Maetsuyker and Council, 26 January 1661.

24. NA, VOC 1232, fl. 383, Letter of Governor Laurens Pit and his Council of Coromandel to the Directors in Amsterdam dated 9 August 1660.

25. NA, VOC 884, fl.703, Letter of Governor Van Goens and his Council in Colombo to the Directors in Amsterdam dated 4 November 1660.

26. Letter of Antão Proença to Paul Oliva, the superior-general of the Society of Jesus, from Tiruchirapalli in 1662, in Joseph Bertrand, La Mission du Madure d’ après de Documents in Edits, 4 vols, Paris, 1847-54, see vol. III, pp. 124-5.

27. Joseph Bertrand, La Mission du Madure, vol. III, pp. 129-30.

28. NA, VOC 1232, fl.1263, fl. 682v.

29. Matheson Library, Monash University, Australia, Microfilm Records, Amsterdam Chamber, VOC 1266.

30. GM, vol. V, p. 133.

31. GM, 11 December 1679, p. 367.

32. Ibid., p. 354.

33. Ibid., p. 370.

34. GM, vol. IV, p. 294, p. 354 (11 December 1679); SLNA, Minutes of the Governor and Council in Colombo, 21 November 1678, fl. 61v-62.

35. GM, 19 March 1683, p. 569.

36. NA, VOC 1234, fl.125v, Letter of Van Goens from Colombo to Jakarta, 5 April 1661; See ‘Beschrijvinge van de staat en gelegenheid van het eijlant Ceijlon door Van Goens, dated 24 September 1675’, in F. Valentijn, Oud en Nieuw-Oost-Indien, Dordrecht-Amsterdam,1724-6, vol. V, pp. 204-45; NA, VOC 1315, fls. 3306-312, ‘Overgeleverd advies dir.-genl. Van Goens met betrekking tot de toestand van Ceijlon, dated 7 November 1676’; NA, VOC 1351, fls. 2539v-2550r, Vertoog van den toestand des gouvts Ceijlon door oudgouvr Van Goens de Jonge van Ceijlon, dated 25 February 1680; P.A. Leupe, Vertooch wegens den presenten staet van de generale Nederlantse Geoctroijeerde Oost-Indische Compe bij Rijckloff van Goens, extr ord raed van India ende commandeur over de retourvloot van Ao. 1655, Bijdragen tot de Taal-Land-en Volkenkunde, 1856, pp. 141-80.

37. GM, vol. III, p. 793 (31 January 1672).

38. SLNA, 1/20, Minutes of the Governor and Council in Colombo, fl.27v-28 (29 October 1674), fls. 35r-36 (3-26 November 1674).

39. SLNA, 1/20, Minutes of the Governor and Council in Colombo, fl.27v-28, fls. 35v-36.

40. NA, VOC 891, fl. 142.

41. L. Hovy, Ceylonees Plakkaatboek, vol. I, pp. 227-8 (5 December 1685).

42. NA, VOC 1506, fls. 1604-5 (31 May 1692).

43. Sophia Pieters, trs., Memoir of Hendrick Zwaardecroon, Commandeur of Jaffnapatam, 1697, Colombo, 1911, pp. 6-7.

44. Knaap Gerrit, ‘Europeans, Mestizos and Slaves: The Population of Colombo at the end of the Seventeenth Century’, trans. Robert Ross, Itinerario, vol. V, 1981, pp. 84-101, see p. 96.

45. Ibid.

46. NA, Verzameling Buitenlandse Kaarte, Leupe (hereafter VEL), no. 1083.

47. NA, VEL 1087.

48. Ibid.

49. NA, VEL 1089,

50. J.A. Van der Chijs, Nederlandsch-Indisch Plakaatboek, 17 vols., Batavia/ S. Gravenhage, 1885-1900, vol.1, pp. 409-10.

51. J. Armstrong and N. Worden, ‘The Slaves, 1652-1834’, in Elphick and Giliomee, eds., The Shaping of South African Society, pp. 109-83; N. Worden, Slavery in Dutch South Africa, Cambridge University Press, London, 1985, p. 9.

52. N. Worden and G. Groenewald, Trials of Slavery: Selected Documents Concerning Slaves from the Criminal Records of the Council of Justice at the Cape of Good Hope, 1705-94, Van Riebeeck Society, Cape Town, 2005, Criminele Verklaringen, 1702-49, pp. 3-4.

53. M.P. De Chavonnes, The Reports of Chavonnes and his Council, and of Van Imhoff, on the Cape, Van Riebeeck Society, Cape Town, 1918, pp. 87-8.

54. Ibid., pp. 101, 112.

55. Western Cape Archives (hereafter WCA), Council of Justice (hereafter CJ), 786 Sententiën, 1736-43, fls. 263-70, translated in Worden and Groenewald, Trials of Slavery, pp. 165-8.

56. Ibid., CJ 786, Sententiën, 1736-45, fls. 236-70, 1739, Cupido van Mallabar, translated in Worden and Groenewald, Trials of Slavery, p. 167.

57. Tamil Nadu State Archives (hereafter TNSA), Chennai, Kantoor Bengalen te Chinsura en Rechtsopvolgers, Boxes 1677A, 1677B, 1679A, 1679B, 1694, 1696 and 1715.

58. WCA, Cape Town, Miscellaneous File, N 49, Serrurier Papers, Transfer deeds of slaves, 1763-6.

59. WCA, Miscellaneous File, M 49, Serrurier Papers.

60. Nira Wickramasinghe, Slave in a Palanquin: Colonial Servitude and Resistance in Sri Lanka, Columbia University Press, New York, 2020, p. 60.

61. Ibid., p. 47.

62. SLNA, MSS 1/4146, 21 August 1784, Anna Maria Giethoorn and Spadille.

63. SLNA, MSS 1/4146, 17 April 1787, Cadieraavan and Lechumee.

64. Arsip Nasional Republik Indonesia (ANRI), Jakarta, Vendutiekantoor, 1, 1751-01-01, 1751-03-30.

65. ANRI, Vendutiekantoor, 1, 1751-04-29.

66. British Library, Oriental and India Office Collections, P/252/76, fl.791, Letter of Charles Oakeley to Jacob Eilbracht dated 14 February 1792.